<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations requiring greater care for trade in England, and some expedients proposed</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34349</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18961</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11751829</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11751829</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34349)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 486:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations requiring greater care for trade in England, and some expedients proposed</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Crouch,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48603:1"/>
            <p>CONSIDERATIONS Requiring greater Care for Trade IN ENGLAND, AND SOME <hi>Expedients Propoſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>S. Crouch,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48603:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48603:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CONSIDERATIONS requiring greater</hi> Care for TRADE <hi>in</hi> ENGLAND, <hi>and ſome Expedients Propoſed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>'TIS very well known, that ſince the Diſcovery of the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> and increaſe of Navigation thereon, the ſtate of <hi>Europe</hi> in general, and every Nation in it in particular, is much altered, more eſpecially in the courſe of War; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before it was ſupplied by Souldiers, either voluntary or bound thereto by Tenure of Lands, who found their own Arms and Cloaths, and for a certain time Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; ſo that War was but of little Expence to the State, and often decided by a Field-Battle (as that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Algiers</hi> and <hi>Tunis</hi> laſt Year) whereupon the Men went every one home again to his own Houſe; now we ſee all corners of <hi>Europe</hi> crouded with liſted, diſciplined, and ſtanding Armies in Pay, which as it cannot be done without huge Funds of Money, and the Ancient Demeſnes of Princes not ſufficing, Taxes are every where increaſed on the Subject; to the end the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of which may be kept open, as 'tis reciprocally needful the State ſhould by all means conſult increaſe of Wealth to the People, (no other ways ſupplied ſo well as by Home Manufacture and Foreign Trade) accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly a change of the Management of War in <hi>Europe</hi> is not more obvious, than the Methods uſed to furniſh ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary deniers for it in the Subject: Therefore in this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48603:3"/> Age, not only Republicks, but even the moſt Abſolute Monarchies, do ſedulouſly court Improvement of their Wealth by Trade, witneſs <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Sweden, Florence,</hi> nay, the Popedom; nor are we ſo to dread the Monſter Arbitrary Power, as to conceive the ſame Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that lead every Man to proportion Burdens to the ſtrength of his Animal, and yield a Paſture to the Milch Kine, will not alſo cheriſh ſo much Mercy and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the worſt Princes, as not to extort more from their Subjects than they have any Means or Ability to raiſe.</p>
            <p>Nothing is more demonſtrative than <hi>(point d'Argent, point de Suiſſe)</hi> no Money, no Souldiers; and no greater obſtruction to the Succeſs of Arms than want of Pay, beſides the increaſing uſe of Fortifications, Artillery, and Fire-Engines is coſtly; wherefore that State which has moſt Money, may have moſt Men, and will be moſt like to have her Enterprizes ſucceed: Whoever thinks the Valour of a few may counter-balance the Numbers of an Enemy, or that an unexperienced Army can ſtand againſt a Veterane, will run mighty hazard of being deceived; and tho' the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ancient Victories in <hi>France</hi> were ſufficient to breed in us a concluſion of the former, yet now a change of the Diſcipline of Arms puts Men under a nearer equality, ſo that whoever conſiders the courſe of our late and preſent Wars, may obſerve the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor moſtly to exceed in Number; beſides War now adays is not determined by Point of Honour, and Dint of Sword, ſo much as by manifold Intrigues, wherein Gold has obtained the Reputation of a Vertue Superla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>As an Alteration of the ſtate of War in <hi>Europe</hi> requires unuſual Supplies of Money from the Subject, 'tis as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that the ſupport of Eſtates in Peace does now alſo call for Supplies much enhanc'd of thoſe in former Ages,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48603:3"/> for Demeſnes, the Ancient ſupport of Crowns, are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally embezelled, the Nature and Form of Courts, the Courſe of Alliances, Intrigues, and Negotiations are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, Officers of all ſorts multiplied, Frauds complicate and inveterate, beſides the accurrence of ſtanding Troops. Wherefore I conclude ſome extraordinary care is to be taken, that increaſe of Wealth in the Subjects may enable them to bear ſuch new Burdens; for if maintenance of the State require increaſe of Revenue when the Subject's Purſe is exhauſted, as in the preſent caſe of <hi>Denmark,</hi> it muſt needs make both King and People uneaſie; and whatever Country this happens in, will be expoſed to danger of becoming a Prey to ſome other.</p>
            <p>To draw down a Conſideration of the Premiſes to a nearer relation with <hi>England,</hi> I take for granted Money is now more than ever the Nerve of War, and Trade the great Miniſter of Wealth; and if every Nation in <hi>Europe</hi> be Armed at all Points, that a Poſture of Defence, even in Peace, is neceſſary to be maintain'd by us; 'tis a greater Bleſſing than the unthankful People of <hi>England</hi> eſteem it, to have the Ocean for our Circumvallation and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier, which Fences us againſt Surprize and Ravages, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes the Charge and Terror of Garriſons and Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and continues to us that Quiet, Liberty, and Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of former Ages, all the reſt of Chriſtendom, more or leſs, have loſt; nevertheleſs an Iſland muſt have a Line alſo of moving Caſtles, Marine Force is ſo increas'd, and all Maritim Nations provided for Invaſion, that we ought to conclude our ſelves no longer ſafe than our Naval Strength is ſuperiour, or at leaſt equal to that of our Neighbours.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak of Power at Sea, and the Advantages it gives Poſſeſſors of it, is a very large Theme, and we need not go back to <hi>Tyre, Athens, Carthage, Venice,</hi> and the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <hi>Normans</hi> or <hi>Danes</hi> to enquire into her Wonders,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48603:4"/> our late and more experienc'd Ages yield as fruitful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: Trade and Power at Sea are productive one of another, the former indeed ſeems Naturally entituled to Parental Honour, though ſhe can no more ſlouriſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Protection of Authority, than the Royal Navy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her, ſo that a Diſcourſe of them may run as of one Intereſt. In the Invaſions of the <hi>Romans, Saxons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> this Iſle was unequal to them in Ships at thoſe Junctures, though at ſeveral other times it was, and ever ſince the laſt has been upon the Offenſive, and ſo exempted from the Broils of <hi>Europe,</hi> more at leiſure to become Umpire and Ballance of it; even ſince increaſe of Navigation we have (bleſſed be God) been ſo happy as to maintain a Force at Sea, which has given Terror to other Nations rather than Encouragement to Invade us; but ſhould it ever arrive (which God forbid) to have the Tables turned upon us, the ill Effects would be ſo much greater as our Security from ſuch Attempts has hitherto been, our Coaſts being eaſie of Acceſs, and not ſo planted with Forts as thoſe long accuſtom'd to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and the Union of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> which wholly rely on us, does not diminiſh but increaſe our neceſſity of Strength at Sea.</p>
            <p>Before Diſcovery of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> there was little Traffick in the Ocean, the <hi>Hans-Towns</hi> and <hi>Flemings</hi> had what was; but when <hi>Spain</hi> had of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Spoils of <hi>America,</hi> ſo over-topt the reſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> as to make ſome fair offers for the Univerſal Monarchy of it, other Nations became enquirers after thoſe Mines, and among them all, none made more Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Advances to a Participation with her than <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> the Hiſtory of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and our large Plantations give Evidence of it, and under that Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queen our Navigation reach'd the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> and <hi>Muſcovy;</hi> the Traffick of the <hi>Hans-Towns</hi> was here
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48603:4"/> extinguiſht, and our <hi>Eaſt-India, Turkey</hi> (if not <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can)</hi> Companies had their Foundations. How Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſince has improved with us, the whole World can Witneſs, and that we may continue to equal, or exceed every Nation on Earth, is, if God permit, not improbable, our Stituation, Harbours, Productions, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, Genius, Timber, and Nautick Skill afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Encouragements to hope it.</p>
            <p>Every Country in meaſuring its own Strength, muſt taken in a Computation of her Neighbour's to make a right Eſtimate thereof, and 'tis this Conſideration alone which can give Jealouſie to our Honour and Welfare: The Neighbour-Nations which can only affect us, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Eclipſe our Glory, diſturb our Quiet, or endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger our Safety, are <hi>France, Spain, Holland, Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Sweden; Spain, Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> are as yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Enterprize on us, ſo that <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>France</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall under a watchful Conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holland</hi> (whoſe Seven Provinces are little more in extent than <hi>Yorkſhire)</hi> is well known to have received the Birth of her Common-wealth ſince increaſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, and is formed entirely to Encouragement of it; what Wealth, Strength, and Conſideration in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> ſhe has obtained by that means, needs no Proof: Moreover the long Wars, wherein ſhe firſt lift up her Head, and ſcarce intermitted, with which ſhe has been ſince exerciſed, have trained her to Modern Diſcipline of Arms, and enured her Subjects to ſuch Taxes, that about 30000 Souldiers, and between 30 and 40 Men of War are maintained by her in time of Peace, and more than doubled in War without difficulty; Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fleets, and ſtanding Armies, and eſtabliſhed Funds for them, are things which ought to give Jealouſie; nevertheleſs increaſe of Wealth ſeems her chief aim, ſhe has Enemies at Land, her Government not compoſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48603:5"/> for Foreign Conqueſts no more than the Genius of the People, and <hi>England</hi> has many Advantages of her both for War and Trade.</p>
            <p>However I ſhall Remark here, that as Trade in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> aroſe and has thriven, chiefly through the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Nature, and Genius of her People; in <hi>Holland</hi> it neither aroſe from the Productions of the Soyl, as in <hi>Aegypt</hi> and the <hi>Baltick;</hi> or from the peculiar Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of her People, as in <hi>France,</hi> and ſome Towns in <hi>Germany;</hi> or from Accident, as in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal;</hi> or from meer Neceſſity, as in <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Genoa;</hi> or from the Amaenity of her Clime, all four Elements conſpiring to thwart it; or from Situation, for when ſtanding on the ſame Platform with <hi>Flanders,</hi> ſhe was infinitely out-ſtript by it; but plainly from the Intereſt of Trade being interwoven with her Original Scheme of Government: And 'tis from a ſteady purſuit of that Policy ſhe has Triumphed over Nature, and Envy of Crowned Heads, and lives like a <hi>Salamander</hi> in the Flames of War, which conſume all beſides her. From this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample I crave leave to infer, that the <hi>Bon-minn</hi> of a Government is more Productive of Commerce than all Advantages of Nature.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, for Reaſons above-mentioned, <hi>Holland</hi> is not to be feared, in compariſon with <hi>France,</hi> the Scourge of this Age, which has a People Martial in their Nature, or made ſo by Diſcipline of ſome Ages, and ſtands poſſeſt of all the Arts of War, and whoſe immoderate Succeſs has juſtly alarm'd all Chriſtendom, though we might ſit unconcerned, were not her Naval Force alſo proportionably increas'd. The Crown of <hi>France, Anno</hi> 1624. was not Owner of one Ship, but hired of her own Subjects, and of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> thoſe ſhe then uſed to Aſſault <hi>Rochell.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> in that Juncture came to the Management of Affairs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48603:5"/> and obſerving thereon how <hi>France</hi> lay open to the Arms of <hi>England,</hi> made it his principal care to provide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch an Inconvenience, and ſo effectually, that <hi>Anno</hi> 1637. <hi>France</hi> ſet out her firſt Line of Battle, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining above 50 Ships, and 20 Galleys, with which ſhe recovered the Iſlands of St. <hi>Margaret</hi> and <hi>Honorat</hi> near <hi>Thoulon,</hi> then poſſeſs'd by the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and <hi>Anno</hi> 1642. <hi>Richlieu</hi> dying, left above an Hundred Ships and Galleys, with Stores ſuitable, in the Royal Arſenals: how her Fleets have been increaſed ſince, to the Terror of <hi>Italy, Spain,</hi> and all the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Shores, let Hiſtories relate; I only obſerve, that <hi>England</hi> has been ſo far from forbidding her to build Ships of War in the Ocean (as 'tis ſaid Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth) that we have been at leaſt unconcerned Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, if not Contributors to it; nevertheleſs we have little felt the Effects of a ſtupid Contempt of that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Growth till this War, wherein <hi>France</hi> has twice diſputed even Dominion of the Channel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> was ſo unacquainted formerly with the Sea, that her Language wants a proper term for the word, <hi>Fleet;</hi> and it appears, that though the Native Riches and Extent of the Country might enable her Monarch to maintain a Royal Navy without the ſubſervience of an anſwerable Trade, yet that alſo was cultivated by the care of <hi>Richlieu;</hi> for <hi>Rochel</hi> and the Cautionary Towns being ſubdued <hi>Anno</hi> 1630. the Proteſtants were for many Years indulged Liberty: And 'twas found <hi>France</hi> had Materials of her own Growth for Building and Rig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Ships; from 1642, to <hi>Anno</hi> 1660, became a Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis as to this matter, through the Confuſions of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King's Minority, and a Civil War, but ſince that time Plantations have been Eſtabliſhed and Improved in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> an <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company formed by Royal Charter, with great Priviledges, Fiſhery encouraged, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Channels, and all Conveniences to Traffick cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48603:6"/> Manufactures invented, and wonderfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, Cuſtoms on Port Trade above all Taxes avoided, Courts of Merchants for deciding all Affairs of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce eſtabliſh'd in moſt of her Great Cities; in fine, no Contemptible Trade has been raiſed in the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean</hi> from <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> and I queſtion if <hi>Dunkirk</hi> is more improved by Land in Fortifications, than by Sea in Traffick and Shipping ſince 'twas ours.</p>
            <p>Dominion of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Seas, eſpecially the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, is not only an undoubted Prerogative and Right of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> but the brighteſt Gem in it: To the Nation 'tis a Wall of Braſs, and the greateſt Bulwark of our Religion, Laws, and Properties; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which all other Proviſions will be too ſhort to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them: And ſhould <hi>France</hi> ever obtain it, how heavy would the Yoak of our Slavery be, or Conflict diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to prevent it? Her Coaſt runs Parallel to ours, her Armies are above 300000 Men, her Gentry Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous and Warlike, Pretenſions ſhe never wants to her Neighbours Poſſeſſions, nor Ambition, Reaſon of State, or Envy of our Wealth, nor Thriſt of Revenge for our Ancient Glories over them; we may confidently aver, that the Miſeries of this Iſland under the <hi>Roman, Saxon, Dane,</hi> and <hi>Norman</hi> Invaſions, and all their Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages, Cruelties, and Impoſitions, would be far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by thoſe the Tyranny of <hi>France</hi> would bring with it, with more danger of continuance alſo: So much is ſaid only to awaken us from that profound Security, our former Victories over her, a flouriſhing Power at Sea, Dominion of the Channel, and long Peace have nouriſh'd in us.</p>
            <p>But to withdraw our Eyes from ſo black a Proſpect, and be ſatisfied that the Gracious God has cut out ſo much Work for <hi>France,</hi> there's no fear of that <hi>Dilemma</hi> during this War; our Wealth accumulated by long
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48603:6"/> Peace, good Condition of the Navy Royal, and mighty Stock of Shipping for Trade at beginning of the War, with a Powerful Conſederacy by Land, Conjunction with <hi>Holland</hi> by Sea, and Renowned Vertue of our King, cannot fail (under God) to ſecure from it: But whereas Trade has extreamly ſuffered, and our Loſſes in it been ſuch, as muſt have overwhelmed any other Nation, and which, unleſs better ſecured and improved, will doubtleſs expire in few Years, our National Wealth, and Naval Power muſt find much difficulty to ſurvive, when <hi>Holland</hi> increaſed in the one, and <hi>France</hi> in the other by our Spoils, ſhall become more Formidable to us.</p>
            <p>Whereas Wealth is now the Meaſure of every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion's Strength, more than the Valour of its Natives, (the latter being enſlaved, and only ſubſervient to the Goddeſs <hi>Money,</hi> as in the inſtance of <hi>Switzerland)</hi> and this War is much more deſtructive to the Wealth of <hi>England,</hi> than to that of any other Country concerned in it; 'tis a Conſideration, which, though it ought not to leſſen our Devotion to ſo good a Cauſe, yet ought to excite us to furniſh our ſelves with the means of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing and more effectually promoting it, a Supply of Souldiers being much eaſier found than Money; in like manner, whereas the Barrier of our Iſland is a Naval Force, our Loſs ſuppoſed of 2000 Ships, whereof near 1000 gained to the Enemy, the decay of our Native Timber, and inhancement in Price of Foreign, the Tranſmigration of Trafick, and a Check upon the Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of our Seamen, require us to retrieve all by double Diligence, ſince the ſtrong Confederacy now againſt <hi>France</hi> may in our particular future Exigence no Wayes be ſafely relyed on.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48603:7"/>
            <p>Upon the whole, I know nothing ſo probable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtate <hi>England</hi> in her Treaſure exhauſted, and Naval Strength periſhing by this War, as ſome new Securities and Encouragements to Commerce; if all that has been deſired of the Government had been conſulted in its Favour, and our Loſſes came only from the unavoidable ſtroak of Heaven, or uſual Fate of Arms, it were Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, and highly unworthy to Complain; but that the Cruiſers and Convoys appointed by King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, have been defective in their Duty, and that Complainants have found little Regard or Redreſs from the Lords of our Admiralty, is too notorious: This is ſaid in relation only to Loſſes in the preſent War, but as to new Securities and Advantages requirable to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem us from the Fatal Conſequences of thoſe Loſſes, we muſt inſiſt on former and long Grievances to Trade, under which, though it has been able heretofore to ſtruggle, yet there are many Reaſons to fear it cannot poſſibly for the future; which Reaſons are taken from a change of the Balance of Trade and Naval Power in <hi>Europe,</hi> which this War has already, and muſt further produce.</p>
            <p>Some Papers touching the Balance of Trade have been Printed, wherein is ſeen how all Countries em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their ſtudy to render it Advantagious, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, before this War 'tis plain how <hi>France</hi> for Twenty Years preceding had gradually beaten out our Exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thither, and turned the Balance vaſtly to her own Advantage; ſeveral other Countries have done the like by us of late Years, in particular, touching Woollen Cloath, generally now Fabrick'd by thoſe who uſed to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd hence; ſo as whoever will give himſelf the pains to enquire into the Acqueſts other Nations have made upon our Trade, and then add the diſmal Effects of this War, will find no ſolid Grounds to expect that <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48603:7"/> ſhould recover her former Glory, Wealth, and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at Sea, without ſome new Advantages to Traffick from the Government; which if it had in any propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to what other Countries give (as already inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced) the God of Nature has ſo bountifully ſupplied all furtherances, we ſhould no doubt out-ſtrip our Emulous Neighbours, and perhaps out-ſhine our Ancient Glories; for to Vindicate and Entail our Dominion of the Seas, I account more deſirable, than to ſound our Trumpets again in the Gates of the <hi>Louvre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a Man went about to enumerate Immunities and Advantages <hi>Holland</hi> gives Trade, it would be ſaid, he had an inclination to ſuch a Government as that; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I here declare once for all, I no more envy <hi>Holland</hi> its Government than I do <hi>France,</hi> and I prefer our Conſtitution before any other whatever; I know nothing wherein 'tis ſo defective as in the Argument be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, and if Navigation was more encouraged, no ways apprehend how the Royal Prerogative would be invaded by it, any more than the Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Liberties of the People; nor would it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that a Monarchy abounding in Territory, ſhould purſue the Methods of Commerce in a Common-wealth, which has nothing elſe to truſt to, any more than that a Gentleman, who may Hunt every day within his own Grounds, ſhould put himſelf behind a Counter: If any ſay, Commerce cannot be ſo conſulted in a Monarchy as a Common-wealth, I ſee no reaſon for ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from the Nrture of the thing, and am not of that mind; for though in former Ages Common-wealths have generally moſt abounded in it, that has aroſe chiefly from their Situation, want of <hi>Terra firma,</hi> or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Accident, and does not amount to a Concluſion againſt Monarchy; for Trade was in all Ages, till with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48603:8"/> little more than a Hundred Years paſt, counted a contemptible thing, as it is ſtill by ſome Mighty and Famous Kingdoms, and is indeed but a Modern System of Politicks, little deſcanted on by the greateſt Writers and Profeſſors of that Science, and ſo not only out of the way of our Domeſtick Studies, but eſteemed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily deſcrepaut with them, though in thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms wherein it has been cultivated, I do not ſee but Trade has ſlouriſh'd by as haſty degrees as in any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths: I confeſs, where the Monarchy is Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, there can be no Security for any thing; and unleſs the Prince's Wiſdom over-rules and purſues the good of Trade, as a Maxim of State, Merchandize muſt be more obnoxious to Rapine than Inheritances of Land; but where the Will of the King is circumſcribed by Laws, there is as much Security as can be in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and I can ſee no Obſtacle to the Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of Trade, ſo the State conclude it her appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Under the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy</hi> how did Commerce flouriſh at <hi>Antwerp</hi> and <hi>Bruges,</hi> ſeveral Ages before the Rabid Fury of the Duke <hi>D' Alva?</hi> Never did Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more Improve in any Country than ours under Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> People were ſafe in the increaſe of their Eſtates, and her Prerogative was neither Eclipſed, or her Learning tarniſh'd by it. <hi>France</hi> did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it a Care worthy of the State till about Sixty Years ago; what ſtupendious Advances has ſhe made? And but for that Check given by the miſtaken Politicks of extirpating Proteſtants, how much greater might they not have been? We might obſerve the ſame things of <hi>Portugal, Florence, Sweden,</hi> and others; but whereas they have been only under certain Princes, and at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Periods, and followed by intervals of Relaxation,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48603:8"/> beſides that I ſuppoſe it no other Fate than has attended Common-wealths which have paſt their <hi>Zenith,</hi> and declined, I will obſerve that among the Princes of all thoſe Nations before cited, the wiſeſt and braveſt have given moſt Encouragement to Navigation and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; and in the Periods they have had their higheſt Aſcendant, Navigation and Commerce have rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed as a Cauſe, than followed as an Effect only. From all which Inſtances I infer, there is nothing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Eſſence of Monarchy, which contradicts the Argument pleaded for.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>England,</hi> if Navigation be the Source of her Wealth, and Wall of her Defence, and after this War, will be the only means of maintaining ſuch a Fleet in readineſs, as can continue the Bleſſings of Liberty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from our Anceſtors, and will be to us a better Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity than Fortifications, Garriſons, and Armies, and will eſtabliſh on our Iſland the Glory of being the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of <hi>Europe;</hi> 'tis therefore concluded the greateſt Intereſt we have to purſue, and being no ways Injurious to Royalty, we may promiſe our ſelves from His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, who has already acquired Heroick Immortality in our Reſcue from Fatal Miſeries, whatever is needful to preſerve us from the like in futurity. And His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Gracious Conceſſions to <hi>Scotland,</hi> in a late Act of Trade, are a particular Pledge to us of his Royal Favour in any ſuitable Requeſts for <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As I have referred the Reader already to ſeveral Books and Papers Printed of Trade, to make ſome Computation of the Ballance of it, ſo I muſt here to inform himſelf of the particular Incumbrances on it; in general I beg leave to ſay, that ſeveral Countries in <hi>Europe,</hi> nay, Monarchies, give more Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48603:9"/> and ſtudy the Advancement of it more, and if Traffick with us ſtand upon daily increaſing Diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, in Compariſon to other Nations, 'tis not like to remain long with us; whether the Alteration of the Exchange lately to moſt Foreign Parts, of near 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Prejudice to <hi>England,</hi> be not a ſad Symptom of her approaching <hi>Exit,</hi> I leave others to Judge, though if our own Naval Power and Wealth were to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued without her, that Conſideration would have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of diſmal in it; 'tis plain His Moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſees clearly a Neceſſity of ſome new Proviſions on this behalf, by that Gracious Propoſal of Laws for the Advancement of Trade, in his Speech to this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for the Subject in caſes wherein the uſual Methods are not adequate to new Emergencies, there our proper Remedy muſt be ſought in Parliament.</p>
            <p>The ſeveral diſadvantages of Trade are not hereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be inſiſted on, our Parliament is too Numerous a Body to have Particulars Examined, Debated, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; the generality of her Members unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Trade, the Houſes taken up with multiplicity of Buſineſs, beſides a time of War is not ſeaſonable for ſuch a Diſquiſition; howbeit ſome of her Grievances have already been touch'd, and in part relieved by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as in the Act appropriating 43 Convoys or Cruiſers for Enſurance of Traffick near our Coaſts du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the War; but alas, there are moſt Conveniences in Port, and thoſe who buy Places are not over-officious to loſe their Lives; whereas the ſame under Direction of the Merchants might have ſaved probably above half our Loſſes. The Sum of what is fit to be requeſted of our Repreſentatives is, for the Conſiderations herein before mentioned, and for as much as the Ancient Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs of the Kingdom have deſiſted from the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48603:9"/> Scheme of ſending Reſident Members (and no doubt in all regards, except Trade, more to the Kingdom's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit) and it would be Interruption to other urgent Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in the Seſſions of Parliament to deſcend into the detail of Merchantil, <hi>That An Act might Paſs to Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute A Council of Merchants,</hi> Sedentary at <hi>London,</hi> and veſted with Powers only adapted to Improvement and Security of home Manufacture and Foreign Trade for the future.</p>
            <p>Only the allowable Paſſion of Love to his Native Soil, and no particular Loſs at Sea, or Perſonal Intereſt in Traffick (the Author no whit concerned) dictates theſe Lines, and he would rejoyce as much to ſee the End conſulted by any other means as theſe here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. I find on the Reſtauration, King <hi>Charles</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to erect a like Council, from his own Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the wonderful Benefit of ſuch in Foreign Parts, and need of it for the welfare of Trade in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> In fine, the Committees at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Merchants, might have produced deſired Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: The proper work of this propoſed Council might be during War, to offer Directions to the Admiralty for Aſſignation of the Convoys (as beſt Judges of the dangers of Ships) and preſcribe time of Sailing to our moſt diſtant Voyages. In Peace, to enquire narrowly into the Balance of Trade with every Nation, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine due making of Manufactures, to draw up Reſults and Methods for Improvement of Navigation and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and intend ſtudiouſly the welfare of them in every regard; in ſome caſes to determine of themſelves, in others to have recourſe to the Privy-Council or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty, in others to digeſt Matters for Information or Sanction of Parliaments. All which may be eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived to the vaſt emolument of the Kingdom, without
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48603:10"/> interſering (I conceive) with any part of our Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
            <p>But if any love Contention, I think whoever ſeeks an Intereſt for the People ſeparate from that of the Crown, and thoſe who deſire one in the Crown deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the People's, are equally Publick Enemies; and I wiſh there was in the Political the ſame Care, Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and Tenderneſs, as is in the Members of a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Body. It would be eaſie to accumulate particular Advantages from the Expedient mentioned, to the King and Parliament diſtinctly, beſides the general ones al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready quoted, and thoſe peculiar to Tradeſmen; but ſuppoſe the Clergy and Nobility ſhould not find herein any particular Intereſts, yet the ſame Principles of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Honour which lead them in other things, will direct to concur to the National in this; and ſince it comprehends equal Proviſion for all Claſſes of Trade, I exhort thoſe concerned not to bury themſelves ſo much in the welfare of their particular Companies, or Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Concerns, as to deſpiſe or neglect that of others and future Ages, no Man more auſpiciouſly conſulting Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Wealth by other means, than by ſerving his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, he may inward Peace, and future Bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let a Bill be tendred this Parliament, with a Computation of Loſſes to the Port of <hi>London</hi> ſince the War, as a Foundation of praying the above ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and there is reaſon to hope Succeſs, ſince 'tis no more than needs, to ſet us on ſome tolerable Level with other Nations, and perpetuate Wealth and Navigation, which are the Security of <hi>England,</hi> no more than right Reaſon dictates that Merchants ſhould direct in Affairs of Traffick, no more than the Nature and End of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms warrant to expect, no more than has been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48603:10"/> granted the <hi>Scots</hi> in their laſt Seſſion of Parliament, and His Majeſty in his late Gracious Speech to ours, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites to ſue for; and God forbid our chief Intereſt for preſerving this Kingdom, ſhould through our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault be loſt under the beſt King it has had ſome Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years; for however invaluable Bleſſings otherwiſe we enjoy under this Government, they are all lodged in the Veſſel of the Common-wealth, and muſt Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack with it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:48603:11"/>
            <head>Some Books lately Printed.</head>
            <p>AN Eſſay on the State of <hi>England,</hi> in Relation to its Trade, its Poor, and its Taxes, for carrying on the War againſt <hi>France.</hi> By <hi>John Cary,</hi> Merchant in <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Letter from an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> to his Friend at <hi>London,</hi> concerning the Trade and Coin of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Row</hi>'s Speech at the Council-Table, about the Alteration of the Coin, in <hi>July</hi> 1640. With ſome Obſervations thereon.</p>
            <p>Some Thoughts concerning the better Security of our Trade and Navigation, and carrying on the War againſt <hi>France</hi> more Effectually: Humbly offered to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>Some Remarks on a Report containing an Eſſay for the Amendment of the Silver Coins. By Mr. <hi>William Lownds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A New Diſcourſe of Trade, wherein is recommended ſeveral Weighty Points relating to Companies of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, the Act of Navigation, Naturalization of Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and our Woollen Manufactures, the Balance of Trade, and the Nature of Plantations, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, in Relation to the Kingdom, are ſeriouſly diſcuſſed. And ſome Propoſals for Erecting a Court of Merchants for determining Controverſies relating to Maritine Affairs, and for a Law for Transferring of Bills of Debt, are Humbly offered. The Second Edition. By Sir <hi>Joſiah Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>De Jure Maritimo &amp; Navali:</hi> Or, A Treatiſe of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs Maritine, and of Commerce. In Three Books. The Fourth Edition. By <hi>Charles Molly.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
